<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="psmith@apache.org">Paul Smith</author>
    <title>Chainsaw v2 Documentation</title>
  </properties>

<body>
		<section name="Chainsaw v2 - Introduction/Table of Contents">
    	<p>Welcome to the home of Chainsaw v2!</p>
      
      <p>Chainsaw v2 is a companion application to Log4j written by members of the Log4j development
      community. Like a number of Open Source
      projects, this new version was built upon inspirations, ideas and creations of others. 
      Chainsaw v2 has it's roots from the original Chainsaw utility written by Oliver Burn, 
      and with inspiration from the Log Factor 5 utility contributed by ThoughtWorks Inc. </p>
    <ul>
     <li><a href="#WhatIsIt">So what is it really?</a></li>
     <li><a href="#QuickTour">Quick Tour of Chainsaw features</a></li>
     <li><a href="#ProjectStatus">Project Status/Support/Feedback</a></li>
     <li><a href="#Installation">Installation</a></li>
     <li><a href="#GettingStarted">Getting Started</a></li>
     <li><a href="#Tutorial">Tutorial and User Manual</a></li>
     <!--<li><a href="#Screenshots">Screenshots</a></li>-->
     </ul>
    </section>
    
<section name="So what is it really?">
      <p><a name="WhatIsIt">&#160;</a>It's a GUI-based Log viewer. A picture tells a thousand words...</p>
      
      <p><img src="chainsaw-1.jpg" width="873" height="492"/></p>

      <p>These screen shots were taken on Windows 2000, running Sun JDK 1.4.2.</p>
      
      <p>Rather than rely on a combination of tail/grep/vi or equivalent to view/query/trace-through
      a huge trail of logging events, you can use Chainsaw.  Chainsaw can read log files formatted in Log4j's XMLLayout, receive
      events from remote locations, read events from a DB, it can even work with the JDK 1.4 logging events.</p>
      <!--<p>You can see some more screenshots <a href="#Screenshots">here</a>.</p>-->
    </section>
    
    <section name="Quick Tour of Chainsaw features">
			<p><a name="QuickTour">&#160;</a> Heres just a <b>brief</b> run down of some of the features of Chainsaw v2:</p>
      <ul>
       <li><b>View remote events</b> - Remote events are "received" by Chainsaw using Log4j 1.3's new Receiver concept.</li>
       <li><b>Saved Preferences</b> - You can fully customize each Tab the way you want it, and it will restore it's state the next time.</li>

       <li><b>Responsive</b> - When events are screaming in, you don't want the GUI to meltdown.  You can control 
       how responsive the GUI is and determine the frequency of updates.</li>
       <li><b>Tabs/Docking</b> - Chainsaw routes separate applications/remote hosts' events to a unique Tab within the GUI.  
       These tabs can be undocked from the main window.  Using these features you can manage multiple application logs using the one GUI.</li>
       <li><b>Coloring</b> - You can specify your own rules to color each event row depending on the attributes of a LoggingEvent to 
       help you locate important events.</li>
       <li><b>Dynamic and powerful filtering</b> - Helps you locate stuff. There's support for quick-and-dirty filtering, right through to advanced expression-based filtering (e.g. <code> "LOGGER == 'com.mycompany' &amp;&amp; LEVEL == ERROR" </code>).</li>
       <li><b>Cyclic</b> - A tab view can support a Cyclic-based model, which constrains it's view to the last
       X events, ensuring you don't hog memory.  This is great for monitoring live applications.</li>
       <li><b>Built-in documentation and tutorial</b> - HTML-based documentation included in the package.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Installation">
			<p><a name="Installation">&#160;</a>Currently you need to check out the jakarta-log4j module from the Apache CVS server
			to build and run Chainsaw v2.  To make this easier, we have created a temporary installation Ant script, you can download this 
			by <a href="install-chainsaw.xml">clicking here</a>.</p>    
			<P>You will need the following installed to utilise this installation script:</P>
			<UL>
			 <li>JDK 1.3+ (1.4.2 is <b><i>strongly</i></b> recommeded)</li>
			 <li>Ant 1.5+</li>
			 <li>CVS (<a href="http://www.cygwin.com/">Cygwin</a> is handy for Windows users)</li>
			</UL>
			<P>Once you have downloaded and placed this script in a directory where you want Chainsaw v2 installed, you can type:</P>
			<pre>ant -f install-chansaw.xml</pre>
			<P>This will download everything you need to build and run Chainsaw v2.</P>
			<P>When finally released, we plan to have Chainsaw v2 available via Java WebStart.</P>
    </section>

    <section name="Getting Started">
			<p><a name="GettingStarted">&#160;</a>Once you have used the above installer, you can <code>cd</code> to tho <code>jakarta-log4j</code> sub-directory and
			type:</p>    
			<pre>ant chainsaw</pre>
			<P>Chainsaw v2 will be built and run!</P>
    </section>
   
    <section name="Tutorial and User Manual">
			<p><a name="ExtraDocs">&#160;</a>Chainsaw already includes help with
      with a Quick Reference and a Tutorial to get you started, all viewable from <b>within the GUI</b>. A User Manual will be made available around release time. </p>    
    </section>

    <!--<section name="Screenshots">
			<p><a name="Screenshots"/>Here's a few more screenshots to whet your appetite:</p>    
    </section>-->
    
</body>
</document>
