<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="psmith@apache.org">Paul Smith</author>
    <title>Chainsaw v2 Documentation</title>
  </properties>

<body>
		<section name="Chainsaw v2 - Introduction/Table of Contents">
    	<p>Welcome to the home of Chainsaw v2!</p>
      
      <p>Chainsaw v2 is a companion application to Log4j written by members of the Log4j development
      community. Like a number of Open Source
      projects, this new version was built upon inspirations, ideas and creations of others. 
      Chainsaw v2 has it's roots from the original Chainsaw utility written by Oliver Burn, 
      and with inspiration from the Log Factor 5 utility contributed by ThoughtWorks Inc. </p>
    <ul>
     <li><a href="#WhatIsIt">So what is it really?</a></li>
     <li><a href="#QuickTour">Quick Tour of Chainsaw features</a></li>
     <li><a href="#ProjectStatus">Project Status/Support/Feedback</a></li>
     <li><a href="#GettingStarted">Getting Started</a></li>
     <li><a href="#Tutorial">Tutorial and User Manual</a></li>
    </ul>
      
    
    </section>
    <section name="So what is it really?">
      <p><a name="WhatIsIt"/>It's a GUI-based Log viewer. Pictures tell a thousand words...</p>
      
      <p><img src="api/org/apache/log4j/chainsaw/doc-files/Chainsawv2.gif" width="873" height="492"/></p>

      <p>These screen shots were taken on Windows 2000, running Sun JDK 1.4.2.</p>
      
      <p>Rather than rely on a combination of tail/grep/vi or equivalent to view/query/trace-through
      a huge trail of logging events, you can use Chainsaw.  Chainsaw can read log files formatted in Log4j's XMLLayout, receive
      events from remote locations, read events from a DB, it can even work with the JDK 1.4 logging events.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Project Status/Support/Feedback">
      <p><a name="ProjectStatus"/>Currently Chainsaw v2 is not in official release status, more
      Alpha level, but a number of developers
      are actively using it to assist in the management of production environments.  A number
      of changes and features are still being added at this time, but it is scheduled to be officially
      released with the Log4j 1.3 release in the very near future.</p>
      
      <p>Feel free to monitor and participate in discussing Chainsaw on the <a href="mailto:log4j-user@jakarta.apache.org">Log4j User</a> mailing list.
      
      Support for the product will also be provided through this forum.</p>
      
    </section>
    
        
    <section name="Quick Tour of Chainsaw features">
			<p><a name="QuickTour"/></p>
      <ul>
       <li><b>View remote events</b> - Remote events are "received" by Chainsaw using Log4j's new Receiver concept.</li>
       <li><b>Responsive</b> - When events are screaming in, you don't want the GUI to meltdown.  You can control 
       how responsive the GUI is and determine the frequency of updates.</li>
       <li><b>Tabs/Docking</b> - Chainsaw routes separate applications/remote hosts' events to a unique Tab within the GUI.  
       These tabs can be undocked from the main window.  Using these features you can manage multiple application logs using the one GUI.</li>
       <li><b>Coloring</b> - You can specify your own rules to color each event row depending on the attributes of a LoggingEvent to 
       help you locate important events.</li>
       <li><b>Dynamic and powerful filtering</b> - Helps you locate stuff. There's support for quick-and-dirty filtering, right through to advanced expression-based filtering.</li>
       <li><b>Cyclic</b> - A tab view can support a Cyclic-based model, which constrains it's view to the last
       X events, ensuring you don't hog memory.  This is great for monitoring live applications.</li>
       <li><b>Built-in documentation and tutorial</b> - HTML-based documentation included in the package.</li>
      </ul>
    </section>

    <section name="Getting Started">
			<p><a name="GettingStarted"/> </p>    
    </section>
   
    <section name="Tutorial and User Manual">
			<p><a name="ExtraDocs"/>Chainsaw includes help with
      with a Quick Reference, Tutorial, and User Manual, all viewable from within the GUI. </p>    
    </section>
    
</body>
</document>
