<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="cgu@apache.org">Ceki Gulcu</author>
    <title>Contact us</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Bug reporting">

<p>Bugs should be reported by using the 
<a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla">Apache Bug Database</a>.</p>

<p>Before reporting a problem, please <a
href="http://nagoya.apache.org/bugzilla/query.cgi">check the
database</a> and the <a href="HISTORY">project history file</a> to see
if the problem is not already known. After this verification step, you
are highly encouraged to send email to the <em>log4j-user</em>
mailing list (see below) describing the bug. Only after these
precautionary steps should you file a bug report.</p>

</section>

<section name="Mailing lists">

<p>Discussion on log4j and logging in general are held on the
<em>log4j-user</em> mailing list.  To subscribe to
this list send an e-mail to <A
HREF="mailto:log4j-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">log4j-user-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org</A>.</p>

<p>Development related discussions are held on the <em>log4j-dev</em>
mailing list. To subscribe to this list send an e-mail to <A
HREF="mailto:log4j-dev-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">log4j-dev-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org</A>.</p>

<p>All developers are encouraged to subscribe to the
<em>log4j-cvs</em> list which will notify the subscribers of CVS any
commits to the repository.  To subscribe to this list send an e-mail
to <A
HREF="mailto:log4j-cvs-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org">log4j-cvs-subscribe@jakarta.apache.org</A>.
Committers <em>should</em> subscribe to this list with their Apache
e-mail address.</p>

<p><b>To prevent spam, we expect you to be subscribed to a list before
posting to it. Otherwise, your mail needs to be approved by an
administrator which delays your posting and creates needless work for us.</b></p>

<p>Most Jakarta mailing lists, in particular the log4j mailing lists,
are archived. Some of the known archives are listed below:</p>

<ul>

<li>
<a href="http://www.mail-archive.com/">http://www.mail-archive.com</a>
</li>

<li>Full mbox archives of all Jakarta lists are available at <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/mail/">http://jakarta.apache.org/mail/</a>
</li>

<li>
<a href="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com">http://marc.theaimsgroup.com</a>
</li>

</ul>

<p>Please do your best to ensure that you are not sending HTML or
"Stylelized" email to the list.  If you are using Outlook or Outlook
Express or Eudora, chances are that you are sending HTML email by
default. There is usually a setting that will allow you to send "Plain
Text" email. </p>




</section>

</body>
</document>

