<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <author email="cgu@apache.org">Ceki Gulcu</author>
    <title>log4j project</title>
  </properties>

<body>

<section name="Introduction">

<p>Inserting log statements into your code is a low-tech method for
debugging it.  It may also be the only way because debuggers are not
always available or applicable.  This is often the case for 
distributed applications.</p>

<p>On the other hand, some people argue that log statements pollute
source code and decrease legibility. (We believe that the contrary is
true).  In the Java language where a pre-processor is not available,
log statements increase the size of the code and reduce its speed,
even when logging is turned off.  Given that a reasonably sized
application may contain thousands of log statements, speed is of
particular importance.</p>


<p>With log4j it is possible to enable logging at runtime without
modifying the application binary. The log4j package is designed so
that these statements can remain in shipped code without incurring a
heavy performance cost. Logging behavior can be controlled by editing
a configuration file, without touching the application binary.</p>

<p>Logging equips the developer with <i>detailed context</i> for
application failures. On the other hand, testing provides quality
assurance and confidence in the application. Logging and testing
should not be confused. They are complementary. When logging is wisely
used, it can prove to be an essential tool.</p>

<p>One of the distinctive features of log4j is the notion of
<i>inheritance</i> in categories. Using a category <em>hierarchy</em>
it is possible to control which log statements are output at
arbitrarily fine granularity but also great ease. This helps reduce
the volume of logged output and minimize the cost of logging.</p>

<p>The target of the log output can be a file, an
<code>OutputStream</code>, a <code>java.io.Writer</code>, a remote
log4j server, a remote Unix Syslog daemon or even a NT Event logger.</p>

<p>On a 233 MHz ThinkPad running JDK 1.1.7B, it costs about 46
nano-seconds to determine if that statement should be logged or
not. Actual logging is also quite fast, ranging from 79 micro-seconds
using the SimpleLayout, 164 micro-seconds using the TTCCLayout and
around a millisecond when printing exceptions. The performance of the
PatternLayout is almost as good as the dedicated patterns, except that
it is a lot more flexible.</p>

<p>The package is being constantly improved thanks to input from users
and code contributed by authors in the community.</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>

