<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<document>
  
  <properties>
    <author email="BMarlborough@thoughtworks.com">Brad Marlborough</author>
    <title>LogFactor5 Features Users' Guide</title>
  </properties>
  
  <body>
    <section name="LogFactor5 Features">

      <h3><font color="#000099">Manage Log Messages</font></h3>

      <p>The Log Table pane shows the listing of LogRecords that have
	been sent to the LogFactor5 appender. The newest log messages
	appear at the bottom of the table.
      </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_logtable.gif" align="absbottom" alt="Log Table" width="600" height="489"></img></p>

      <h4><font face="Verdana, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif" size="3"><a name="levels"></a></font>Log 
	Level Selection </h4>

      <p>The LogFactor5 toolbar applies directly to the Log Table
	area. Log levels can be toggled on and off to filter out
	messages that you want to view or hide. Levels include FATAL,
	ERROR, WARN, INFO and DEBUG. </p>


      <p><img src="images/lf5_loglevels.gif" width="600" height="488"
      alt="Log Levels"/></p>

      <p><a name="color"></a><b>Log Level Color Configuration</b></p>

      <p>To help distiguish the various log events displayed in the
	LogTable, LogFactor5 allows users to set the colors of their
	log events based on level.</p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_colorchooser.gif" width="600"
      height="489" alt="Log Level Color Configuration"/></p>
      
      <h4><a name="search"></a>Full Text Searching</h4>

      <p>The Log Table supports full text searching. To perform a
	search, choose Edit-&gt;Find from the menu bar or CTRL-F and
	then enter the text you want to search for.  LogFactor5 will
	find any strings that are an exact match for the string you
	entered. Pressing F3 will find the next occurrence of the
	string.
      </p>
      
      <p><img src="images/lf5_search.gif" width="600" height="488"
      alt="Full Text Searching"/></p>

      <h4><a name="views"></a>Log Table Views</h4>

      <!-- =========================================================== -->
      <!-- In the next paragraph, changed category to logger, priority --> 
      <!-- to level, LogRecord to event. (Ceki)                        -->
      <!-- =========================================================== -->
      <p>The Log Table has three views; compact, standard and
	detailed. The compact view only displays the Nested Diagnostic
	Context (NDC), logger and message.  The standard view is the
	default view, and displays the level, NDC, logger and message
	of the logging event. The detailed view displays, in addition,
	the date, message number, location (i.e. the method that is
	logging the message), thread description and the
	throwable. The view selector on the toolbar switches between
	the three views. Columns in the Log Table can be re-sized and
	moved by interacting with the column headers.
      </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_view.gif" width="600" height="489"
      alt="Log Table View"/></p>
      
      <h4><a name="recorddetails"></a>Log Record Details</h4>
      
      <p>The Log Record Detail area displays all of the attributes of
	the LogRecord which is selected in the Log Table. When a row,
	or LogRecord, is selected in the Log Table, the complete
	details of that LogRecord are displayed in the LogRecord
	Detail area, independent of the view in effect.
      </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_recorddetail.gif" width="600"
      height="481" alt="LogRecord Details"/>
      </p>

      <!-- ============================================================ -->
      <!-- In the next 2 paragraphs, changed category to logger. (Ceki) -->
      <!-- ============================================================ -->
      <h4><a name="explorer"></a>Logger Explorer</h4>

      <p>The Logger Explorer area enables the filtering of incoming
	log messages based on logger. If a logger is deselected
	(no checkmark is shown next to it) then new messages on that
	logger will not be displayed. The Logger Explorer has no
	effect on log messages already in the Log Table.
      </p>

      <p>The Logger Explorer displays loggers in a hierarchical
	tree-like fashion.  Loggers are identified with
	dot-separated names similar to Java package and class
	names. The name components are mapped to the levels in the
	hierarchy in the Logger Explorer. For example, the logger
	name org.apache.applications.log4j.InitUsing Log4JProperties
	is displayed below: 
      </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_category_explorer.gif" width="600"
	  height="481" alt="Logger Explorer"/></p>


      <h4><a name="selectloggers"></a>Selecting and Deselecting Loggers</h4>

      <p>When a logger in a hierarchy is deselected, no messages at
	that level or below will appear in the Log Table. For example,
	if just the first InitUsingMultipleAppenders logger in the
	examples.InitUsingMultipleAppenders.InitUsingMultipleAppenders
	logger is deselected, then messages with the logger examples
	would be displayed in the Log Table, but messages with the
	logger InitUsingMultipleAppenders.InitUsingMultipleAppenders
	would be filtered and not displayed in the Log Table. 
      </p>

      <p>To quickly select or deselect loggers in the hierarchy,
	the right-mouse button can be used to bring up the pop-up menu
	displayed below. </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_deselectall.gif" width="600"
	  height="488" alt="Deselect All Descendants"/></p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_selectall.gif" width="600"
	  height="488" alt="Select All Descendants"/></p>
      

      <h4><a name="expandcattree"></a>Expanding and Collapsing the Logger Tree</h4>
      
      <p>You can also expand and collapse the hierarchy tree using
	the pop-up menu displayed below.</p>
      
      <p><img src="images/lf5_expandall.gif" width="600" height="488"
      alt="Expand Tree"/></p>
      
      <p><img src="images/lf5_collapseall.gif" width="600"
      height="488" alt="Collapse Tree"/></p>
      
      <H4><a name="ndcfiltering"></a>NDC Record Filtering</H4>


      <p>Log4j provides a lightweight technique for stamping log
	requests initiated from the same client within a multithreaded
	system. The Nested Diagnostic Context (NDC) provides an easy
	way to differentiate logging output of one client from
	another. The NDC is also useful for differentiating log
	messages being output by different members of a large
	development team building an application on the same
	server. To improve the sorting of potentially thousands of log
	records being output from multiple clients, a NDC filter has
	been provided. To use the NDC filter, select the Edit menu
	item and choose 'Sort by NDC'. Fill in the name of the NDC you
	would like to filter on. All records containing the filter key
	word will be displayed in the Log Table. To restore all of the
	log records use the Edit -&gt; Restore all NDC's. You can also
	use the Edit-&gt;Find feature to locate NDC's without removing
	log records from the Log Table. Furthermore, you can use the
	Configure-&gt;Save feature to persist the last NDC filter key
	word that was used. Note however that restoring all NDCs will
	effectively erase the NDC filter key word. Refer to the <a
	href="#configuration">Configuration section</a> below for more
	information on saving NDC filter key words.</p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_ndc_filtering.gif" width="600"
      height="488" alt="NDC Filtering"/></p>


      <font color="#000099"><h3>Read Log Files</h3>
      </font> 

      <h4><a name="readfile"></a>Read a File</h4>

      <p>LogFactor5 supports reading in log files that were created
	using log4j's RollingFileAppender.  The benefit of this
	feature is that developers who run utilities like Ant to test
	their applications can now view their log files off-line
	(i.e. after their application has completed the test and the
	JVM has shut down). Reading log files currently only works for
	files written a LogFactor5's unique ConversionPattern.  For
	more information on setting the LogFactor5 conversion pattern,
	please see the OpeningLogFiles example. To open a file and
	read it into LogFactor5, you need to start the logging console
	using the StartLogFactor5Console.bat file provided in the bin
	directory. Once the console is open, choose File-&gt;Open from
	the menu at the top of the GUI.
	</p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_openfile.gif" width="600" height="488"
	  align="absbottom" alt="Log Table"/></p>

      <h4><a name="readurl"></a>Read a File From a URL</h4>

      <p>LogFactor5 supports reading log files created using log4j
	from a URL. Having the ability to open log files on a remote
	server provides the ability for multiple developers working on
	the same application to view log files independently.  It also
	gives developers the ability to view log files both internally
	and from remote locations. Reading log files currently only
	works for files written a LogFactor5's unique
	ConversionPattern. For more information on setting the
	LogFactor5 conversion pattern, please see the <a
	href="example7.html">OpeningLogFiles</a> example. To open a
	file and read it into LogFactor5, you need to start the
	logging console using the StartLogFactor5Console.bat file
	provided in the bin directory.  Once the console is open,
	choose File-&gt;Open URL from the menu at the top of the GUI.
	</p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_openurl.gif" width="600" height="488" align="absbottom" alt="Log Table"/> </p>

      <p><a href="#top"><font size="2">&lt;&lt; Return to Top of Page &gt;&gt;</font></a></p>
	
      <font color="#000099"> <h3>Configuration</h3></font> 

      <h4><a name="configuration"></a>Save Configuration Information</h4>

      <p>LogFactor5 allows you to save your current
	configuration. When you choose the Configuration-&gt;Save
	option from the menu at the top of the GUI, the loggers and
	levels that you currently have selected, along with the last
	NDC filter key word used (assuming 'Restore all NDC's' has not
	been selected), are saved to your local file system. This
	means that the next time you start up the console you will not
	need to reselect the loggers, levels, and NDC filter that you
	would like used for filtering.
      </p>

      <p>LogFactor5 also allows you to remove your saved
	configuration, and to configure the maximum number of records
	that will be displayed at any time in the logging
	console. Setting the maximum number of records to display
	allows you to optimize LogFactor5's performance for your
	system. The maximum number of records can also be configured
	via a log4j properties file.
      </p>

      <p><img src="images/lf5_configure.gif" width="600" height="488" align="absbottom" alt="Log Table"/></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>